CHEICK TIDIANE BA

Ph.D. student in Computer Science at Università degli studi di Milano Statale

@ cheick.ba at unimi.it

♀ Lecco, Italy

% back7.github.io



SHORT BIO

Hardworking and people-oriented Ph.D. student in Computer Science at Università degli studi di Milano Statale. Research and programming activities have led to several projects and publications, mainly in the fields of big data analysis, network analysis, bioinformatics.

My experience as a teaching assistant, private tutor and volunteer developed my teaching and training skills.

EXPERIENCE

Ph.D. student in Computer science

Computer Science department - Università degli Studi di Milano Statale

M Nov. 2020 - Now

Milan, Italy

- Research on temporal network modeling and big data mining
- Supervisor: Prof. Sabrina Gaito (CONNETS lab, ex NPTLab)

Teaching assistant

Master degree Data Science and Economics at Department of Economics, Management, and Quantitative Methods - Università Degli Studi di Milano Statale

🗎 Sept. 2020 - Dec. 2020

Milan, Italy

 Practice lecture: graph analysis and visualization with Python, networkx, Gephi. Theoretical lessons: data retrieval, crawling systems

Research assistant (type B)

Computer Science department - Università degli Studi di Milano Statale

May 2020 - Nov. 2020

Milan, Italy

• Supervisor: Prof. Gian Paolo Rossi (CONNETS lab, ex NPTLab)

EDUCATION

Master degree in Computer science - 110/110 cum laude

Computer Science department - Università degli Studi di Milano Statale

Milan, Italy

Bachelor's degree in Computer science for digital communication - 106/110

Computer Science department - Università Degli Studi di Milano Statale

October 2018

Milan, Italy

SKILLS

Best soft skills

Hard working
Problem solving
Teamwork
Training & teaching



Best hard skills

Python
HTML/CSS/Javascript
PHP
SQL
Java
Swift
R

Languages

English (C2)

French (A2)

Italian (C2)

FRAMEWORKS

Machine learning

Keras, Tensorflow, Weka, Scikit-learn and multi-class sklearn

Big data analysis and management

Spark and graphX, MongoDB, PostgreSQL and Oracle DBMS.

Data analysis

Python libraries (statsmodels, scipy, pandas, sqlite3), Excel.

Web & Mobile development

HTML/CSS/Javascript, AngularJS, PHP, nodeJS, mariaDB.
Android Studio and Java, Xcode and Swift

Network analysis

networkX, igraphs. Spark graphX and graph-Frames

PROJECTS

Methodologies for financial group data analysis

 Design of new methodologies for customer segmentation and behavioral-centric financial group risk analysis.

Technologies: Apache Spark, Python

Twitter sentiment analysis

 Classifier for sentiment in Tweets with different neural network architectures (convolutional and recurrent LSTM/GRU with attention) and frameworks (Keras, scikit-learn) working on a Kaggle dataset.

Technologies: Python, MongoDB, LaTeX

Evolution of an online social network

 Supervised learning methods for link prediction a decentralized online social network. I improved prediction performance with a novel methodology, relying on text-based features (using LDA models for user similarity).

Technologies: Python, MongoDB, Jupyter Notebook

Indoor positioning Library

Design and development of indoor positioning library in Java.
 The library relies on data from the camera, inertial sensors, and Bluetooth beacon to locate a smartphone. The library was used in an Android application for indoor navigation.

Technologies: Java, Android, PHP

Distributed system for sensor data

 A system composed of a REST server, a client for each sensor, an admin UI.

Clients create mesh networks and coordinate themselves to aggregate sensor data: the result is stored on the server, for admin monitoring.

Technologies: Java

The NBA on Youtube

 Analysis of the interaction network for users commenting on the NBA's Youtube account. Focus on interaction networks and sentiment analysis in comments.

Technologies: Python

LEGO AR Tools

Development of an Augmented Reality App for the visualization of instructions for Lego models. The project was realized for iOS platforms. Collab. with another student.

Technologies: Swift, XCode, NodeJs (REST server)

Rumor Tracker

 Rumor detection tool for Twitter posts. The tool implemented a clustering-based method for the extraction of topics from a stream of tweets.

Technologies: Python, MongoDB, LaTeX

Unipred-Web

 Design and development of a web interface for the integration and prediction of bio-molecular networks. I helped with web UI and database design and development, APIs.

Technologies: HTML/CSS/JS, AngularJs, Cytoscapejs, NodeJs (REST server), Git, LaTeX, MariaDB

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

- Perlasca, Paolo, Marco Frasca, Cheick Tidiane Ba, Jessica Gliozzo, et al. (2020). "Multi-resolution visualization and analysis of biomolecular networks through hierarchical community detection and web-based graphical tools". In: *PloS one* 15.12, e0244241.
- Perlasca, Paolo, Marco Frasca, Cheick Tidiane Ba, Marco Notaro, et al. (2019).
 "UNIPred-Web: a web tool for the integration and visualization of biomolecular networks for protein function prediction".
 In: BMC bioinformatics 20.1, pp. 1–19.

Conference Proceedings

- Ba, Cheick Tidiane, Matteo Zignani, et al. (2020). "The Effect of Cryptocurrency Price on a Blockchain-Based Social Network". In: International Conference on Complex Networks and Their Applications. Springer, pp. 581–592.
- Ba, Cheick Tidiane, Elena Casiraghi, et al. (2018). "A Graphical Tool for the Exploration and Visual Analysis of Biomolecular Networks". In: International Meeting on Computational Intelligence Methods for Bioinformatics and Biostatistics. Springer, pp. 88–98.